{"tossups": [{"question": "One side in this battle halted fire due to a miscommunication about the remaining ammunition; to maintain morale, that side informed its men that the pause was to have breakfast. The direction \u201cyou may fire when you are ready, Gridley\u201d was given to begin this battle. In this battle, George Dewey\u2019s U.S. fleet lost one sailor to heatstroke and sunk 8 Spanish ships. For ten points, name this May 1, 1898 battle of the Spanish-American War, fought in the harbor of the Philippine capital city.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Manila Bay</b> (do not prompt on Manila alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An army from this region intercepted King Josiah at Megiddo and killed him. Near the end of his life, the prophet Jeremiah was forced to move to this region against his will. A family fled to this region to escape King Herod\u2019s decree to kill all boys two years or younger. The firstborn of every household in this region was slaughtered before its leader allowed the Israelites to leave. For ten points, name this region that, in numerous Biblical stories, was ruled by pharaohs.", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man sacked the castle of Jacob\u2019s Ford after a bribe of 100,000 gold pieces to stop the castle\u2019s construction was turned down. Though this man was defeated at the Battle of Montgisard, he later formed a truce with Baldwin IV. One campaign against this man was called after his victory at Hattin, though he ended that conflict by granting Christians safe pilgrimage to Jerusalem. For ten points, name this Kurdish founder of the Ayyubid dynasty, an enemy of Richard I in the Third Crusade.", "answer": "<b> Saladin</b> (or An-Nasir<b> Salah ad-Din</b> Yusuf ibn Ayyub)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This team lost a group of promising young players in the 1958 Munich air disaster, though a survivor of that crash, Bobby Charlton, held the goalscoring record for this club until 2017. A manager who gave locker room tirades known as \u201chairdryer treatments\u201d won 13 Premier League titles with this club, which is currently managed by the Portuguese former manager of Chelsea, Jos\u00b4e Mourinho. Sir Alex Ferguson once coached, for ten points, what English soccer team led by Zlatan Ibrahimovic and Wayne Rooney?", "answer": "<b> Manchester United</b> F.C. (prompt on Manchester and/or United alone; prompt on ManU)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Contemporary historian James Ronda has written several books about this event, one of which claims that a comparable event was led by James Mackay and John Thomas Evans. During this event, Fort Clatsop was constructed along the Columbia River. Participants in this event included a slave named York, Toussaint [too-sahn] Charbonneau, and Charbonneau\u2019s Shoshone wife, Sacagawea. For ten points, name this voyage that explored the Missouri River, including much of the Louisiana Purchase.", "answer": "<b> Lewis and Clark</b> Expedition (accept<b> Corps of Discovery</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In ancient times, this currency was worth 6 obols. In 1828, the phoenix replaced the Ottoman kurus, then itself was replaced four years later by the \u201cphoenix,\u201d adorned with King Otto\u2019s face; both this currency and the phoenix were equivalent to 100 lepta. In 1973, this currency replaced the image of the deposed King Constantine with more phoenix imagery and the phrase \u201cHellenic Republic.\u201d For ten points, name this currency used by both the ancient and modern, pre-Euro Greeks.", "answer": "<b> drachma</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man testified on behalf of Robel Phillipos after the Boston Marathon bombing. In 1988, this man fired Donna Brazile for claiming his opponent was cheating with Jennifer Fitzgerald. During a presidential campaign, this man was attacked for supporting prisoner\u2019s weekend furlough passes in the Willie Horton ad and for opposing \u201cvirtually every defense system\u201d in the Tank ad. For ten points, name this former Massachusetts governor who lost to George H.W. Bush in 1988.", "answer": "Michael<b> Dukakis</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This only piece of music this composer wrote for harp was a concerto featuring it with flute. This compoeser\u2019s twenty-fifth piano concerto is nicknamed \u201cCoronation\u201d for its use during the ascension of Leopold II to Holy Roman Emperor. An opera by this composer, whose aria \u201cDer Holle Rache\u201d is known for its coloratura high Fs, had a libretto by Emmanuel Schikaneder that was probably inspired by Freemasonry. The Queen of the Night is found in, for ten points, what composer\u2019s<em> The Magic Flute</em>?", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus<b> Mozart</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This state\u2019s capital was chosen to be at the site of LeFleur\u2019s Bluff, overlooking the Pearl River. An alluvial plain in this state, home to the towns of Clarksdale and Greenville, is bounded on the east by the Yazoo River and is known for a distinctive variety of blues. Another city here was captured after a 47-day siege by Ulysses S. Grant in 1863. For ten points, a namesake Delta and the city of Vicksburg are located in what Southern state whose capital is Jackson?", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this Indian empire ruled by Humayun and Akbar.", "answer": "<b> Mughal</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One side in this election year used the song \u201cHunters of Kentucky\u201d to rally support. After suffering a stroke, William Crawford lost support and finished third in this election year. Thanks to the Twelfth Amendment, this election hung on a House of Representatives vote that the loser decried as a \u201ccorrupt bargain\u201d struck by Henry Clay. For ten points, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams defeated Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "Presidential Election of<b> 1824</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "David Markson\u2019s best known work is titled for this philosopher\u2019s \u201cMistress.\u201d Bertrand Russell\u2019s \u201cThe Philosophy of Logical Atomism\u201d was based on one of this man\u2019s works. This philosopher once threatened Karl Popper with a hot poker because Popper claimed the existence of moral rules. \u201cThe world is everything that is the case\u201d opens a work by this man that he himself later critiqued in his posthumously published<em> Philosophical Investigations</em>. For ten points, name this Austrian philosopher who argued that all philosophical problems were mere \u201clanguage-games\u201d and wrote<em> Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</em>.", "answer": "Ludwig<b> Wittgenstein</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s reign, his forces broke a blockade of the Hanko Peninsula in the Battle of Gangut, his country\u2019s first naval victory. A major victory during his reign was the capture of Azov. He reorganized his government with the Table of Ranks and defeated a revolt by the streltsy. He studied shipbuilding in the Netherlands as part of his Great Tour to learn more about Western Europe. For ten points, name this\u201cGreat\u201d modernizing tsar of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Peter I</b> (or<b> Peter the Great</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a letter to his cousin Lund, the owner of these objects notes that two of them were\u201cin the secret drawer\u201d of a locker. Jean-Pierre Le Mayeur befriended the owner of these objects in 1781 and helped maintain them. A letter asking for equipment to care for these</b> <b>objects noted there was (+)</b> <b>\u201clittle prospect of being in [Philadelphia] soon;\u201d that letter</b> <b>was intercepted by the British and may have convinced Henry Clinton to not reinforce Yorktown. Contrary to (*)</b> legend, wood was<em> not</em> used to fashion a replacement set of these objects, which are now on display at Mount Vernon. For ten points, name these body parts that made public speaking difficult for the first US President.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>\u2019s (false and/or real)<b> teeth</b> (accept clear equivalents; accept George <b>Washington\u2019s denture</b>s or similar equivalents; do not accept Washington\u2019s wooden teeth, as they weren\u2019t made of wood)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In January 2017, protests erupted against this leader over increases in gas prices known as the \u201cGasolinazo.\u201d The \u201cI am 132\u201d movement was established to protest this leader\u2019s 2012 election. This leader was heavily criticized for inaction over the 2014 (+) kidnapping of 43 students in Iguala. This man\u2019s namesake \u201cbots\u201d spread propaganda in favor of him and his party, the (*)</b> PRI. This leader canceled a meeting with Donald Trump after he said his country would refuse to pay for a border wall. For ten points, name this current President of Mexico.", "answer": "Enrique<b> Pe\u02dcna Nieto</b> (prompt on partial last name)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>Athenians who performed a special type of this process were known as cleruchs; the first such example was probably done at Salamis. A brand from an original</b><em><b> prytaneum</b></em><b> was used in the (+) ceremonial beginning of this process, which started taking place in Ionia, Thrace, and Italy in the 700s BC. (*)</b> Syracuse was created as a result of, for ten points, what general process that spread ancient Greek culture and, more crucially, people, throughout the Mediterranean?", "answer": "ancient Greek<b> colonization</b> (accept word forms; accept descriptions of ancient Greeks <b>settling new cities</b> or equivalents; prompt on exploration until \u201cprytaneum\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<em><b> Honeywell, Inc. v. Sperry Rand Corp</b></em><b> overturned a patent created during this project, which was originally called \u201cProject PX.\u201d John Brainerd was the lead investigator during</b> <b>this project, which intrigued John von Neumann enough to lead to its use in (+)</b> <b>H-bomb</b> <b>development at Los Alamos. This project was initially commissioned by the Ballistic Research Laboratory to calculate artillery tables at the University of Pennsylvania, and it became fully operational in 1946. (*)</b> Kay McNulty was one of six women who programmed, for ten points, what \u201cGreat Brain\u201d that is often considered the first electronic computer?", "answer": "<b> ENIAC</b> (accept<b> Electronic Numerical Integrator and Computer</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "<b>This man ended a mutiny by declaring to his men \u201cI am waiting for the tanks and the Americans\u201d before launching another attack. After Erich von Falkenhayn declared that he</b> <b>would bleed this man\u2019s troops (+)</b> <b>white in one battle, this man allegedly rallied his men</b> <b>with the cry \u201cthey shall not pass.\u201d The \u201cSacred Way\u201d supply line was established by this (*) </b>marshal, who worked with Pierre Laval in a post-military position that earned him life imprisonment. For ten points, name this war hero at Verdun who collaborated with the Nazis as the head of Vichy France.", "answer": "(Henri-)Philippe<b> Petain</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The leader of the losing side of this war was killed by a man known as \u201cFrank the Devil.\u201dThe Campaign of the Hills was the final phase of this conflict, which included the siege of the Fortress of Humait\u00b4a. (+) Rutherford B. Hayes helped lead negotiations in the aftermath of this conflict which included the Battle of Tuyut\u00b4\u0131. Eliza Lynch was the wife of the leader of the losing country, which lost over (*) </b> two-thirds of its adult male population. Francisco Solano L\u00b4opez was killed in, for ten points, what war in which Paraguay was defeated by Argentina, Brazil, and Uruguay?", "answer": "War of the<b> Triple Alliance</b> (prompt on Paraguay(an) War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Buffalo Bill rode up to this figure and bowed to her at the Chicago World\u2019s Fair. Ann Gordon argues that pro-life depictions of this figure are an example of \u201cinvented memory.\u201d</b> <b>This woman worked with (+)</b> <b>George Train as the publisher of a weekly newspaper called</b> <em><b>The Revolution</b></em><b>; that paper put her ten thousand dollars in debt, according to testimony in which she declared \u201cI shall never (*) </b> pay a dollar of your unjust penalty\u201d after being arrested in Rochester after attempting to vote. For ten points, name this advocate for women\u2019s suffrage who was honored on a 20th century dollar coin.", "answer": "Susan Brownell<b> Anthony</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}